<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>books on George Paps Blog</title>
    <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/tags/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in books on George Paps Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 17:54:44 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://georgepaps.pages.dev/tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Books read 2024</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/books2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 17:54:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/books2024/</guid>
      <description>In case you need some reading inspiration, here is a list of the books I&amp;rsquo;ve read thus far in 2024. I have highlighted my favorite ones.
Atomic Habits by James Clear - 8/10 Heart of Darkness by Joseph Conrad - 9/10 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books read 2023</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/books2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 17:54:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/books2023/</guid>
      <description>In case you need some reading inspiration, here is a list of the books I&amp;rsquo;ve read in 2023. I have highlighted my favorite ones.
American Pastoral by Philip Roth - 6/10 Les Miserables by Victor Hugo - 7/10 Clear Thinking by Shane Parrish - 6/10 The Comfort Crisis by Michael Easter - 8/10 Xenakis by Nouritza Matossian - 7/10 Benjamin Franklin by Walter Isaacson - 8/10 100 Baggers: Stocks That Return 100-to-1 and How To Find Them by Christopher W.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Favorite Books</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/favbooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 20:54:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/favbooks/</guid>
      <description>The past years I&amp;rsquo;ve read a couple of books. The ones I enjoyed the most are:
Non-fiction:
Black Swan - Nassim Nicholas Taleb Antifragile - Nassim Nicholas Taleb The Bed Of Procrustes - Nassim Nicholas Taleb Hackers and Painters - Paul Graham Flow - Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi Leonardo da Vinci - Walter Isaacson Einstein: His Life and Universe - Walter Isaacson Steve Jobs - Walter Isaacson Thinking, Fast and Slow - Daniel Kahneman Benjamin Franklin: An American Life - Walter Isaacson Why We Do What We Do - Edward Deci The Obstacle Is the way - Ryan Holiday Stillness is the key - Ryan Holiday Ego is the enemy - Ryan Holiday Mastery - Robert Greene The Comfort Crisis - Michael Easter Why Nations Fail - Daron Acemoglu Macroeconomics Beyond the NAIRU - Servaas Storm 21 Lessons for the 21st Century - Yuval Noah Harari Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind - Yuval Noah Harari Essentialism - Greg McKeown The art of the good life - Rolf Dobelli The Pathless Path - Paul Millerd Fiction:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
