<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on George Paps Blog</title>
    <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on George Paps Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 17:54:44 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Books read 2023</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/books2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 17:54:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/books2023/</guid>
      <description>In case you need some reading inspiration, here is a list of the books I&amp;rsquo;ve read in 2023. I have highlighted my favorite ones.
American Pastoral by Philip Roth - 6/10 Les Miserables by Victor Hugo - 7/10 Clear Thinking by Shane Parrish - 6/10 The Comfort Crisis by Michael Easter - 8/10 Xenakis by Nouritza Matossian - 7/10 Benjamin Franklin by Walter Isaacson - 8/10 100 Baggers: Stocks That Return 100-to-1 and How To Find Them by Christopher W.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Favorite Books</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/favbooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 20:54:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/favbooks/</guid>
      <description>The past years I&amp;rsquo;ve read a couple of books. The ones I enjoyed the most are:
Non-fiction:
Black Swan - Nassim Nicholas Taleb Antifragile - Nassim Nicholas Taleb The Bed Of Procrustes - Nassim Nicholas Taleb Hackers and Painters - Paul Graham Flow - Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi Leonardo da Vinci - Walter Isaacson Einstein: His Life and Universe - Walter Isaacson Steve Jobs - Walter Isaacson Thinking, Fast and Slow - Daniel Kahneman Benjamin Franklin: An American Life - Walter Isaacson Why We Do What We Do - Edward Deci The Obstacle Is the way - Ryan Holiday Stillness is the key - Ryan Holiday Ego is the enemy - Ryan Holiday Mastery - Robert Greene The Comfort Crisis - Michael Easter Why Nations Fail - Daron Acemoglu Macroeconomics Beyond the NAIRU - Servaas Storm 21 Lessons for the 21st Century - Yuval Noah Harari Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind - Yuval Noah Harari Essentialism - Greg McKeown The art of the good life - Rolf Dobelli The Pathless Path - Paul Millerd Fiction:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walk your walk</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/walkyourwalk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 12:13:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/walkyourwalk/</guid>
      <description>A phrase I &amp;rsquo;ve been pondering on for some time now is &amp;ldquo;walk your walk&amp;rdquo;. I found that keeping this phrase handy is useful for my mentality. In this post I will share my two main interpretations of it.
The first interpretation relates to personal goal setting. The phrase works as a reminder to keep going, to walk the path that you intended to and not give up when you encounter the first obstacle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review - Gödel, Escher, Bach</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/bookreviews/geb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/bookreviews/geb/</guid>
      <description>Traces of intelligence. Rating: 6/10
In this book the author attempts to formally approach consciousness and to unravel the mysteries of its emergence. An arguably ambitious goal. Surprisingly, what you come to realize throughout the book, is that to some extend he succeeds. His concept of convoluted, multi-level strange loops seems to offer an interesting leeway towards the origins of consciousness. Maybe not the only available, nor the most effective, but nevertheless a viable one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just Write</title>
      <link>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/just_write/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://georgepaps.pages.dev/posts/posts/just_write/</guid>
      <description>Find a system that makes writing and re-writing effortless. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to post everything you write, but it&amp;rsquo;s good to write consistently.
Why do that in the first place though? Because writing is an effective way of thinking. When writing you embark on a mental journey towards unexplored paths. A journey where you both explore and expand your thoughts. And this is an invaluable process hardly accessible by other means.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
